<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An humble representation from His Excellencie Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councel of the Armie; concerning their past endeavours, and now finall desires for the puting of the souldiery into constant pay. For the immediate disburthening the kingdom of free quarter, the prevention of any further encrease of arrears, and in order to the better disbanding of supernumeraries, and other things concerning the souldiery. Humbly presented to the Right Honourable the Houses of Parliament, by Colonell Sir Hardresse Waller, and Colonell Whaley, Decemb. 7. 1647. By the appointment of His Excellencie Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councell of the Army. Signed Jo: Rushworth, Secr. Decemb· 7. Imprimatur Gilbert Mabbott.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84755</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862444</idno>
  <idno type="VID">114603</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240961638</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing F168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E419_16</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201977</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862444</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862444e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84755)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 114603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 66:E419[16])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An humble representation from His Excellencie Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councel of the Armie; concerning their past endeavours, and now finall desires for the puting of the souldiery into constant pay. For the immediate disburthening the kingdom of free quarter, the prevention of any further encrease of arrears, and in order to the better disbanding of supernumeraries, and other things concerning the souldiery. Humbly presented to the Right Honourable the Houses of Parliament, by Colonell Sir Hardresse Waller, and Colonell Whaley, Decemb. 7. 1647. By the appointment of His Excellencie Sir Thomas Fairfax, and the Councell of the Army. Signed Jo: Rushworth, Secr. Decemb· 7. Imprimatur Gilbert Mabbott.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Army. Council.</author>
                  <author>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, Baron, 1612-1671.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for George Whittington, at the Blue Anchor in Cornhill near the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A different edition from F169, which has "printed by John Clowes" in the imprint.</note>
                  <note>A1r is in two settings: line 1 of heading ends (1) "his" or (2) "Humble".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Dec: 8th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">England and Wales. --  Army --  Pay, allowances, etc. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History, Military --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:114603:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:114603:1"/>
            <head>An Humble REPRESENTATJON FROM His Excellency, Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and the Councell of the Army.</head>
            <p>SInce, by the blessing of God, the Speakers and Members of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oth Houses (that had been driven away) were without blood restored, and have been ever since secured to sit and attend their duty in Parliament, with what patience God hath given us to wait for the resolutions of those things we have insisted on or offered, tending to the future security of the Parliament, the just satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the Souldiery, and the ease and settlement of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, we need not use many words to set for<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h; the expence of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 4. moneths time, in quiet expectation thereof, with so little satisfaction does sufficiently speak.</p>
            <p>As to what fruit we have found, in any thing done to any of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:114603:2"/> those ends, we are sorry we can say so little thereof, or that we have occasion to say so much to the delayes, neglects, and obstructions thereof, as now we are constrained to doe,</p>
            <p>But what ever those delayes or neglects have been, or where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the fault hath been, we are sure the blame thereof hath been laid upon us, almost on all hand, and this is the fruit we have found from the hands of men, of all our patient waiting hitherto.</p>
            <p>It is not unknown what reproaches and scandalls in this kind have been cast upon us, and what use and advantage hath been made of those delayes, thereby to work upon the impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Souldiers, and Countrey, to incence the Countrey a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Army, and both the Countrey and Army against us, as if it had been our fault alone, that no more was done. And to what an height of scandall and discontent against us, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence hereof was driven, or what desperate endevours have been thereupon, to withdraw the Souldiers from the Officers (as having betrayed or failed and neglected both theirs and the Kingdomes interest) to divide and distemper the Army, and to engage both the Souldiery and many other well affected people (under the same notion and pretence) in wayes of distraction and confusion, and (as we accompted them) of most imminent dangers, both to the Parliament, City, and K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngdom, we need not now spend time to expresse; We believe all that wisht well to the publike were so deeply sensible thereof, as they cannot so suddenly forget it, and others (who had any thing to lose or hazard) though perhaps so farre as they had hopes, the Army might that way have destroyed it selfe, they might have some secret rejoycing at it, and may now be sory the businesse is so well over without that offer, yea, so farre as they considered the bottomlesse depth and endlesse danger of it, they could not but be aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cted with it, so as we need n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t mention i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> save to mind men of what danger and mischief God hath therein delivered them from, and whence the greatest advantage to the rise and growth of it, was (even from delayes and slow proceedings in those things which the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:114603:2"/> long expectations of the Souldiery and Kingdom have been set upon, and to observe how apt both the Souldiery and people through tedious delayes in such cases, are to hearken to any party, and try any new way proposed (under the notion of more spee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and effectuall, though perhaps so farre from reall remedy as that it indeed endangers the utter losse of their end, with ruine and distruction to both.</p>
            <p>To prevent the progresse of this growing danger to all, we have lately exposed our selves to the utmost hazard, and being acted therein from some clearnesse in our Consciences, that the fault of those delayes lay not upon us [as was scandalously sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gested] and a confidence in God that he would appear, to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate that measure of truth and integrity, he had given us in the thing, though with many failings and miscarriages on our part, we were led forth by him, without any Artifice, whereby to vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate or excuse our selves, nakedly to cast our selves, and the busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse upon him, and to his praise we must speake i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, he hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in an answerable issue; whereof the Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hath had an accompt, and wherein they may see, and we wish they may with us take notice and be mindfull of, the mercy and goodnesse of God in our deliverance more added to all the rest, and therein the Army, which in casting of all bonds of order and government, was like to have been let loose to be a plague and bane both to the Kingdom and it selfe, once more reduced unto that temper and discipline which may render it, through and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God, a further security and stay to the Kingdom, and in due time bring it to a quiet disbanding, when just satisfaction, with settlement and safety, shall admit.</p>
            <p>But [as hath in part been done already] we must again mind the Parliament upon what tearmes this hath been wrought, the Generall [as we all with and under him] stands engaged to the Army, for the lawfull prosecution of the Souldiers Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and some Generall fundamentall things for the Kingdoms and (in confidence of the Parliament good accep ance of the ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:114603:3"/> thereby done, and of there reall intention and promised ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall resolution, to give satisfaction in those things) hath in a manner undertaken for the Parliament therein.</p>
            <p>We wish we may see a cause to acknowledge a just sence of his Excelencies good aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction, &amp; service in that busines, or at least of their owne engagement, or the Kingdoms concernment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, and that we had not cause to apprehend either a strange neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect thereof growing upon many, or rather (in some) the sad sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes of an evill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye, at the service it self, as if they did regret the happy composure of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ose distructions begun in the Army and the reuniting of it, or did grudge the good hand of God towards it, and the Kingdom therein, that in mercy would not suffer it to run on in these distractions to its own ruine and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms. For though it be most evident that had God given up the Army to cast off the reins of Government and order, and to go on in those distracting and confounding wayes, (which it was endeavoured to be drawn into) both it and other forces of the Kingdom, were like ere this time to have been engaged in blood, one against another, or else united onely in some desperate course of rending and tearing out the bowels and vitals of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and plucking up or endangering all foundations of order, peace and government therein (yea and of all right and property too) yet the envy and ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ignity of some mens spirits against this Army, and against the interests of good men therein, seems to be such, as if they had rather have seen it so, then that this Army should again be an united piece; and we clearly apprehend the same principles (that swaid heretofore) none again prevailing, as if there were no good so desirable or evill so formidable; which the breaking of this Army (with as much ignominy, and confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion as may be) would no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, in their accompt, countervail; and if such an envious and evill spirit be indeed lodged and working in the hearts of any, we desire God in mercy to convince them of it, least he confound them for it. For our parts having the witnesse of God in our consciences that though we are not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out weak and frail workings of our fleshly hearts in all our ways yet for the main) we have in all our Engagemen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, from the beginning of the warre, had the work of God and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:114603:3"/> in our eye, and not our own, and that since the Army (by the oppressive provoking and spitefull procced<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of men acted by the aforesaid envious principles a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst it) was raised into such resolutions, and driven into such a posture as put it past the power of the Officer to bring it to a quiet disbanding, without further satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and security; It hath been our main end in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing with it and almost our whole work, to keep it within compasse and moderation, to withhold it from extremi ies of all sorts and from that mischief to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom or it self, which our withdrawing and taking off our hards from the Government of it, would have let it loose unto, to make use of it, and of the providence that brought it to that passe (if possible) to some good issue for the just liberty, safety and settlement of the Kingdom, and bring the Army to some bottom of seasonable satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction wherein it might acquiece, and at last come to a quiet disbanding; and (in transaction of all this) with all tendernesse and patience to preserve [if possible] the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and peace of the Kingdom, and prevent new Broyls, which severall parties and interests have been so apt unto.</p>
            <p>Having, we say, the witnesse of these things within us, when, on the other side, we consider what unworthy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitalls for all this we meet with from the hands of men, how we are loaded with reproaches for it, and rendered the only disturbers of the Kingdom, &amp; the Authors of its burthens, as if for private ends or designes we kept up the Army) &amp; how generally most men [even of the Parliament party, for whose preservation and for prevention of whose ruine amongst others, we have exposed our selves to all ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zards therin) do either from disaffection or design to divide and break the Army, with-hold or obstruct all supplies and satisfaction which might keep it in order, union or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e; We confesse, when we consider these things wee are ready to apprehend that God doth herein seem most just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to upbraid our care and solicitousnesse, to preserve a people given up (as we begin to fear) to their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wn de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction, and which seem to chuse it rather, then not to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:114603:4"/> have their own factious interests or envy fulfilled, rather t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en to own their preservation, in the least degree, by those whom God hath appeared willing to use for their preser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and deliverance.</p>
            <p>And rather then we would further incur the odium and scandall of being the only publike disturbers and oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors (so unworthily cast upon us meerly for our good-will, and endeavours to prevent greater mischiefs) we are apt to chuse rather to withdraw from our presentation (though with hazard of our personall safeties, and the losse not only of any imagined benefit of future employment, but even our arreares, for what service we have done) and so leaving all to what ever confusion God in his righteous judgment may see good to bring upon the Nation, to cast our selves wholly upon him, to preserve and provide f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r us in the middest thereof, or if God in mercy n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d better things to the Kingdom, or hath found ought in us (which wee confesse he may) rendering us unworthy to be an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> further instruments thereof, we should desire, with meeknesse and rejoycing, to see any other whom he finds, or the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom judgeth more worthy to take up our present char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: But finding not as yet any such c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ar discharge as would (to our apprehensions) fully acquit us before God or Man, to leave the Army or kingdom in their present con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, we shall, in discharge of our duty to the u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>most, add this one assay more, to bring both into a be ter, if God in mercy see it good: We shall thereof once more begg the Parliament timely to consider and provide effectually for these things exprest in the late Remonstrance pub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ished at the severall Randezvouz of the Army, vpon his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies continued conjunction, wherein the discontents in the Army were quieted, the distractions composed, and the due order and Discipline of it, recovered and submitted to.</p>
            <p>And amongst these things, since the greatest and most immediate and pressing evill to the Souldiery is want of pay, and to the Countrey, the disorders, exactions, and abuses of the Souldier, with the burthen &amp; annoyances
<gap reason="missing" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ pages">
                  <desc>〈1+ pages missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:114603:4"/> free quarter (thereby enforced) and which (if once provided for) gives time of consideration for other things, we shal first apply to that either to obtaine a present remedy, or at least, to acquit and discharge our selves in that point.</p>
            <p>Of the many evills thereof both to the Souldiery and Country we have long beene sadly sensible, and many wayes and often ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed our sence thereof, but we have bin most troubled at it, since that necessity which heretofore inforced it, (<hi>viz.</hi> the straitnes of the Quarters the Parliament had to raise money in) was taken away, and all parts of the Kingdome have beene cleared, from any enemy, and free for the equall levying of money to supply the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessities of the whole; and it seemes a matter of wonder to us, or an argument of great improvidence (at best) that since that time the Souldiery (though much lessened in number) should be no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter paid or provided for then before; From the sence of these things we have made frequent addresses to the Parliament, for a sufficient establishment and provision of pay for the Army and other Forces of the Kingdome, untill they might (with safety to the Kingdome, and just satisfaction or security to themselves (in point of Arrears. Indemnity <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) be disbanded or otherwise imployed out of the Kingdome, We have long waited with patience as aforesaid, for some fruit of our addresses, at least, in this point: But what through the difficulty or delay of getting things past in Parliament to this purpose, or of putting in execution those Ordinances that have beene passed, and the neglect or slownesse of Country Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, Assessors, or Collectors to do their duty therein, what through the Malignancy of some who (in designe to breake or distract the Army as aforesaid) for want of pay, and to disaffect the Country thereto by necessitated free quarter) doe industriously retard all supplyes of money, and what through the Generall backwardnesse of all (especially in the City of <hi>London,</hi>) to part with it, we have yet found little fruit of all our addresses, and endeavours in this kind, there being not as yet an establishment of Contribution, for pay of the Souldiery, any whit neare proportionable to the numbers that are yet kept up, or any effectuall execution of the powers al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given for raising of the Taxes already charged upon the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:114603:5"/> Kingdome, so as we remaine yet, as farre as ever, from that sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of pay to the army, or other forces, whereby either the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and grievances of free quarter can be taken off, or the neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sity of the Souldiery competently supplyed or t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eir dis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ontents in any measure removed, or disorder prevented or good discipline preserved, and (which is most <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ad) in the Garrisons of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (and tho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e of most importance) where the Souldiery have not, nor can well have that benefit of Quarter for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ubsistance (as the Army and field Forces have yet) they have very long beene without any supply of pay at all, so as divers poore Souldiers in some of them have actually starved, and died for want, in atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon their duties, others forced by extremitie of want to quit their service and the rest ready to sterve or quit the Garrisons to any that will possesse them; And as it is most apparant, that the present proporti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n of Tax (if duly levied) could not competent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly supply them, and others too (in an equall distribution thereof, considering the number that are yet in being) so the Committees in many Countries (where such Garrisons are, that have engaged with the Army) doe refuse to levie those small proportions of money, that have been assigned for the present reliefe to such Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons, but are content to see the aforesaid miseries of the Souldie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and danger to the Garrisons, rather then doe their parts, to give the least remedie to either, divers of them telling the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers plainly (as wee are informed) that if they had declared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the Army, they should not have wanted, but having engaged with it, they must expect neither quarter nor pay, but what they get from the Army.</p>
            <p>If we or this poore Army have deserved such hatred and despite, (especially from pretending friends to the Parliament, and the Kingdome interest) wee would faine be plainly told and convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced wherein, otherwise wee cannot but account it most unchristian and inhumane dealing, and such as can have no better root, then most envious faction, void of all regard to publike Interest; and wee would have all such know, that if we had borne the same mind, or could have alowed our selves by power to pursue the ruine of adverse parties by indirect or unchristian wayes, or otherwise to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:114603:5"/> set up a party of our owne, and suppresse all others, or if wee had not still (according to our first principles) loved much more the wayes of Common right and freedome, and the proceeding in all such things by Parliament in order thereunto, or if wee had not in the way of ordering our affaixes since the Armies ingagement, consulted more the preserving of Peace in the Kingdome, and to prevent the rise of any new warre, then our owne advantage or security, wee could (to speake as men with the power and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages God hath put into our hands) long ere this time (as yet also wee might) have put the Army, and all other Forces engaged with it into such a Posture, as to have assured themselves of pay, while continued, and probably to have made our opposers in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and City too, willing to have followed us with offers of sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, as to Arreares, and other dues that concerne the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d ery; or wee could have told how to prosecute those advantages wee have had to the suppression, if not destruction of adverse par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and interests, so as they should not (probably) have had those foundations or possibilities to grow up againe, to our further trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ot danger (as now they seeme to have;) And all this with reason and justice enough too, but that wee have studied the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation, and good of all, without ruine or destruction to any, as farre as wee could and have (through God) been acted therein, in some measure, with that mildnesse, moderation, patience, and love that becomes the name of Christ; And wee are yet confident, wee shall at last lose nothing by it; But (to returne to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose, as to the inconveniences and dangers of a new Provision for the Souldery in point of Pay, the Parliament hath had sufficient Cautions and warnings, especially in the late distractions; and though, while the danger thereof continued visible, it was largely professed (if that danger could be removed and the Army redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced into order and discipline) we should have what provision wee would with reason in that point, and the same (with much more) upon the first hopes of overcomming that danger, was as largely promised; Yet now the danger is over, wee see little better care of performance then before. but after many dayes since elapsed, and some spent in professed consideration of it, the whole care, of that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:114603:6"/> businesse seemes to be wrapt up in one Bare vote, <hi>viz.</hi> [that all su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernumerary forces shall be disbanded.]</p>
            <p>As to which matter of disbanding supernumeraries (so it bee with reasonable satisfaction in point of Arreares) we are so farre from opposing, or obstructing it, that (for the speedy easing of the Kingdomes burthens by it) wee shall readily give all furtherance and assistance to it, and shall (by and by) offer that incouragement thereto, as will demonstrate the same, and no such tearmes wee should our selves most gladly bee of those supernumeraries that should come first to disbanding.</p>
            <p>But, as to the thought of present disbanding all supernumeraries (according to the Vote) first we cannot but wish it be considered, whether with any respect at all to the service, and reliefe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the Parliament can well disband them all, unto which service (as there might have beene a great advancement of assistance long since, but for the prevalence of Faction and designe to breake that force that might have afforded it, as wee have formerly remonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) so we have more lately contributed our parts, in the offer and designation of a very considerable force thereunto, and there hath wanted nothing but resolution and money, with expedition to send them over, which was not within our power.</p>
            <p>But if (with respect to that service and the safety of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome) the Parliament can yet lessen their forces so much, as to bring them neere the compasse of sixty thousand pounds a moneths pay, yet, wee wish it be withall considered how many those super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeraries are, that must so come to bee presently disbanded (which, to bring the residue within that compasse, would bee little lesse then twenty thousand of one sort or other) and (if so) how great a summe it would require, to give any reasonable satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to so many in point of Arreares in hand; And (by the hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of getting so much money as to piece up the moneths pay to the Army) wee have much reason to doubt how long the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment will be in raising such a summe together, or where they will suddenly find money, to give competent satisfaction to the propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but of a Regiment or two upon a present disbanding, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse they be provided with present money, to give reasonable satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:114603:6"/> to so many at once, as would to that end come to be disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, the Parliament must either turn them off presently with extreame dissatisfaction and disobligation (which would render them apt to rise again with any party against the Parliament who would give them hope of better dealing, or but of revenge) or else must continue them untill better provided.</p>
            <p>And though there were mony ready for a competent part of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears in hand, yet it wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l be necessary however that they be continued some time for the stating of their accounts and giving debentures for the remainder, for (besides the injustice and dissatisfaction of turning the Souldiers off without that) we presume the Parliament hath had too much experience already of the bottomlesse ill consequences of not ascertaining their accounts and arrears before disbanding, and not keeping the same registred together, by the endlesse clamours and out-cries of particular persons for arrears, and the vast summes expended thereupon without end of satisfaction (the persons or their state of ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rears through neglect of taking such accounts before disbanding) ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving never been certainly known, nor any end either of their number or claims) and the dispatch of such accompts, for those that remaine, before disbanding, will certainly take up some time (we doubt) some moneths; now, if thus any part of the supernumeraries (above what the sixty thousand pounds a moneth will pay) shall either for the time of staring their accounts or longer (for want of present mony to disband withall) be continued, both they and all other Souldiers in the Kingdome must so long remaine without constant pay, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequently go upon free quarter the while, unlesse the tax for their pay be (for the mean time) proportionably increased, for the sixty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand pounds a moneth, not affording any assignement for such su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernumeraries pay, those must of necessity go unpayd the while and consequently upon free quarter, and their going any where upon free quarter will hinder the coming in of the contribution of those parts which should be to pay some others, and so they likewise must go up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on free quarter the while, which will in like manner hinder the pay and necessitate the like free quartering of others, so as all wil that while be equally hindered of constant pay, and forced to take free quarter still; but (besides these aforementioned certain and visible occasions of delayes to the present effect of the vote for disbanding all supernu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meraries
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:114603:7"/> (we doubt it will find many other difficulties and obstructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the speedy and effectuall dispatch thereof, and prove not so easie or so well executed as voted; so that though we wish that businesse of disbanding supernumeraries, put into a way of as speedy execution as may be, yet upon all these considerations we cannot imagine that vote to be absolute and soveraigne, nor so speedy or timely a Cure of the Souldiers wants, and discontents, or the Countries grievance in their free quarter, as the nature of the maladie and temper of the Patient requires; Wee shall therefore offer our fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall advice for some other: First setting downe the particulars, and then shewing the efficacy and benefit thereof; The particulars (which we have in part heretofore propounded to the Parliament) are these;</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>That the Parliament do forthwith enlarge their monethly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution for five or six Moneths, to the full proportion of the pay of all the Forces now in being within this Kingdome (or at least of so many of them as they are not provided with present money to disband) and to a considrable proportion</hi> (viz. <hi>about ten thousand pounds a Moneth) over; which (by a neere estimate) we conceive would well be by the addition of forty thousand pounds</hi> per mensem <hi>to the present sixty thousand pounds, and with lesse we beleive it cannot be; And the same Committees to be appointed and to have the same power for the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying of this as for the former sixty thousand pounds, and the same pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties for neglects or defaults therein, as for the Arreares of former taxes to the Army, and for more speedy passing of this unlesse some visible inequallity in the rates of Countries could be readily rectified without delay to the passing of it, we wish it might, (being but for that short space) passe according to the same rates as the sixty thousand pounds; and for the Kingdomes better satisfaction herein it may be Resolved and Declared.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>I <hi>That upon this inlargement and the effectuall Leavying of it in the respective Counties, no free quarter at all shall (from within a month at most after passing the Ordinance) be taken in any County or place where it shall be duly Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vyed and paid.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:114603:7"/>
                  <item>II. <hi>That it is intended this inlargement of tax shall not be continued beyond the space of the months limitted, and that in the meane time, as the Parliament can find money, and safety to disband and lessen their forces, so (if that lesse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning be considerable) they will by degrees lessen the said tax proportionably.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>VVe desire that for the more sure and effectuall Leavying of the whole tax, the Generall and Committee of the army, or one of them may have power (in case of any County Committees neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect or failing therein) to add new men to any the respective Committees who (thereupon) to have the same power as the Committees named in the Ordinance have.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. That for more sure and ready payment of the Souldiery out of this, the forces which cannot, or are not provided for to be forthwith disbanded, may be immediately assigned to severall Counties or Associations of Counties, out of whose taxes they shall be paid, and that the Generall may have power accordingly to make such distribution &amp; assignments giving notice and accompt thereof to the Committee of the Army, and they thereupon to take order for the payment of the forces so assigned, immediately out of the Counties or Associations to which they are Assigned, and that the payment be made according to due Musters and according to the last establishment (as to the rate of each officers pay) and the surplusage of any Counties Taxes above the due pay of their Forces so assigned to be paid out of them, to be (at the care and oversight of the same Committee for the Army) called for and paid into the Common Treasury, for such Generall vses as shall be found necessary relating to the forces and service within this Kingdom, by warrant from the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:114603:8"/> Generall or Committee for the Army according to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suall course of limitations heretofore; and the remainder or surplusage of the said Taxes of the whole Kingdome (above the uses aforesaid) to be for the supply and reliefe of the forces already in <hi>Ireland,</hi> or other publique uses as the Parliament shall thinke fit; And the same Committee likewise, with the Treasurers, to take care for the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodizing, and ballancing of the whole accompts, and to have power for the imploying of Officers needfull for the dispatch and accommodation of this service, and to make allowance of salaries to them, (within some reasonable li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation) particularly that there be allowances for so many Deputy Commissaries of Musters as upon the practick of this distribution, the Generall and Committee shall find needfull; And the Treasurers Generall out, of their salary (in regard of this accession to it) to maintaine so many De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty Treasurers as the Generall and Committee of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my shall find needfull to be imployed, and reside in such severall parts of the Kingdom as the Generall shall find con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient for that service.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That the security for arreares being setled as hath been already and is againe hereafter propounded, the Parliament would speedily send downe Commissioners to the Army, and appoint the like for other forces of the Kingdome, to state accompts and give debenturs, whereby the Souldier may before disbanding, have his arreares ascertain'd to him, as a cleere debt to be paid him out of that security; And that one Office or Registry may be appointed into which all ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compts so taken may be returned, and all the arreares Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistred to be paid in order, as is hereafter exprest, and for this office we offer that two Registers, with four Clarkes maybe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:114603:8"/> allowed to have reasonable Salaries out of the Revenue issuing out of the said security, and this we desire may be hastened for the speedier preparation to the worke of disbanding; that such as are to be disbanded may be ready for it, by that time the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament can provide money where-with to disband any of them, and that so by disbanding the supernumeraries as fast as may be, way may be made for the speedier lessening and taking off the Taxes by degrees.</p>
            <p>Now, for the advantage and benefit of the things here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded, they will appeare as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi> Whereas upon the former supposition (that the putting off the Soldiery that are to be continued into a way of constant pay, do depend only upon the disbanding of all supernumeraries, whom the present Tax will not extend to pay) Its most evident (as before demonstra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) that none can be put into present pay, but all must goe on upon free quarter, so long as untill every one of the said super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numeraries be disbanded (which what ever may be imagined) though no other difficulties or obstructions should happen then what are now visible, as before mentioned, would not be effected, nor (we doubt) provided for in three or foure moneths time, wee wish it prove so soon: but we much feare interruptions, or delayes, will happen to make it much longer, and all that while (free quarter cnotinuing as before) the burthen thereof (besides the anoyances) though it fall more lightly upon some parts and heavier upon others, yet in the whole it damnifies the Kingdom as much as the said increased contributions come to. The Soldiers also must have (besides his quarters) some pay in hand the mean while (otherwise he can neither subsist nor be kept in order) yet still he accounts (at least) half of his pay for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining time, in arrear to him, so as that further debt doth also grow upon the Kingdoms score; Now contrary-wise (the things we have propounded being granted) that bare contribution an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swers all; for we dare under take, within a fortnight after gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of them, all the forces of the Kingdom shall be assigned where, &amp; how to receive their pay constāstly, til disbanded; &amp; so no more freequarter shal hēceforth be taken, no part of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom any more unequally oppressed thereby, nor any further debt of arrears hence forth incurred upon the Kingdom, and the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:114603:9"/> worke of disbanding supernumeraries not at all hindred, but much facilitated thereby, and as the Parliament findes money and safety to disband any of them, they may by the same de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees either lessen the taxe proportionably, or will have so much more surplusage thence from, towards reliefe of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or towards disbanding of others, or any other publique uses.</p>
            <p>And now for furtherance and encourrgement in the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of disbanding (those things afore mentioned being gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) wee shall (for the Armie and other Forces engaged with it) offer and agree to these rules following,
<list>
                  <item>1. That such of the said forces as shall come to be disbanded as supernumeraries, shall (out of the moneys to be raised up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the security for Arreares) have the full moity of their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reares first made good to them, as moneyes come in hereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, before those which fall out to be continued shall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive any part of theirs, and after that (when those that continue, shall have received the like proportion of theirs then) these that shal be disbanded to receive the other moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty or full remainder of their Arreares, before these that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue any more.</item>
                  <item>2. That those of them which shall disband, shall (as moneyes come in upon the said security) receive their proportion of Arreares in the same order and course as they disband, (of which order and course a remembrance to bee entered and kept in the afore-said Regestry of these accompts) the persons of the Regiment, Troope, or Company first disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and so the rest in course, to receive first what was due to them at disbanding (to make up their first moity) by two equall portions, and likewise to receive their second moity at twice, by equall portions, in the same course as they disband.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now for our desire in the first proposition afore-going, (to have the increase of Contribution extended to the proportion often thousand pounds a moneth (by estimate) over &amp; above
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114603:9"/> what we thinke the just pay for the Souldiery now in being in the Kingdome, and not ready for present disbanding will come to: the reason is, partly, that there may bee (certaine) some present supply out at it for the Force in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly because, if the contribution should be set scant of, or but just answerable to the pay of the Souldiery, the many Contingen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and accessary Charges (not to be fore-seen, and the proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble failings of full levying the Contribution in some parts, would necessitate the going of some upon free Quarter, (which would disturb the order, and constant pay of the whole) and it would also require much time to proportion the Forces, to be assigned upon the severall Counties exactly to the contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions of them, which would make it long e're free Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters could be taken off, since none could be assigned where to be paid, untill the pay of each part of the Souldiery were ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly computed, and all of them as exactly distributed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to each Counties taxe;) Whereas the taxes being laid to a sufficient proportion above the just pay, we can immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately make distributions and Assignments lye estimate, so as to be sure the taxes of each County exceed the pay of the soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers assigned to it, and though so, one County have more, and another fewer souldiers assigned to them then (upon an exact distribution according to the number and pay of the Souldiery) their just proportion would come to, yet none ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving so many, but that their taxes wil do more then pay them, no part will beare above its due proportion of charge, and those parts which have least numbers of Souldiers assigned up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, yet will beare their due proportion of charge, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in pay to the Souldiers, or in the surplusage of their taxe above it; which, being collected into the Common Treasu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, will be for relife to <hi>Ireland,</hi> or other publique uses, so as the surplusage (either in particular Counties above their particular Assignments, or of the whole Kingdomes taxes, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the pay of the whole Souldiery in it) will bee no losse; but (as to some present and certaine reliefe for <hi>Ireland</hi> out of it, upon supposition of the hundred thousand pounds a moneth) wee shall (besides the surplusage of every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties taxe above the pay of the Souldiers to be assigned to it)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:114603:10"/> fore-cast in the Distributions and Assignments, to leavye the taxes of some Counties, (and that as many as may be) to come intirely into the common Treasury for the reliefe of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> without assaying any of the Forces in <hi>England</hi> to bee paid out of them.</p>
            <p>And for that power desired for making such Distributions and Assignments, the advantages and benefits of that way of Reperticion (as to the more sure and ready payment of Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers) are sufficiently knowne and tryed: and it is most e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident, that without it, (if no Souldiers be paid before the moneyes he first Collected in the severall Counties, and then sent into the Common Treasury for all the Kingdome, and then sent to the Head-Quarters, or thence distributed to the severall Forces within the Kingdome, it is vaine to think that the Souldiers can be supplyed with money afore-hand, or timely edough to make him pay Quarters, and 'tis as good (almost) not at all, as not in time.</p>
            <p>Wee have thus propounded a way whereby all the Souldie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Kingdome may bee instantly put in a condition of constant pay (while continued) and thereby bee kept in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and discipline, all free quarter (with the abuses, exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, annoyances, and unequall pressures that accompany it) immediately taken off, no further debt of Arreares incurred upon the Kingdome, and that which is already incurred, put in a way to bee recovered and overcome in time, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the supernumerary forces may shortly be disbanded by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees (as the Parliament can finde money to doe it) and will bee satisfiable to disband, with lesse money in hand, without danger of dis-obligation therein, and whereby also the additionall charge (now propounded) with other bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens of the Kingdome may by the same degree be lessened and eased with safety and satisfaction, untill all can bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off.</p>
            <p>And as it is evident, that if such a course as this had been
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:114603:10"/> taken sooner, and the Parliament (as they found the seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts of the Kingdome cleared from the enemy, and eased of the oppressions they suffered under them) had by degrees extended an equall contribution over all parts in a proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on sufficient to have payed all their forces (while they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued them) the Kingdome had been eased of free quarter, and no further debt of arreares to the Soldiery incurred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, for (at least) a yeare and halfe agoe, those that have been disbanded had not been put off with so much dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obligation (as some have been) nor had their claimes and endlesse demands since brought such troubles upon, or drawne such vast arrears from the Parliament and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and those that now remaine to be disbanded had been much easier satisfyable and more readily disbanded; So if such a course (as is here propounded) be not speedily taken, but the putting off the Soldiery into a way of pay be left to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend only, upon the disbanding of all supernumeraries (and that so unprovided for) or so uncertainly and slowly provided for, and proceeded in (as without this course) it is like to be) it is most evident (besides unforeseen dangers of discontent both in the Soldiery and Country of difficulties to disband, or interruptions and dissatisfactions in it) that the non-disband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of some will so long occasion the non-payment of all, and continue free quarter, with the inconveniences thereof upon all, and the non-payment of all may hinder the disbanding of any, and so both debts and discontents grow upon the Soldiery and Kingdome, (perhaps) till it passe the power either of the Generall and Officers, to compose the one, or the Patliament and Kingdome to satisfie the other.</p>
            <p>Having therefore thus sufficiently d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>scharged our selves in this point, so as we shall (we hope) stand acquitted before God and men from whatever evils ensue upon any further neglect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; We must now declare, That we find the just expectations of the Army herein (especially since the Generalls late Eengage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or undertakings at the Randezvouz) are so great and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest, the clamours and outcryes to us from other forces, Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:114603:11"/> of the Kingdome ingaged with the Army (for their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame necessity, and our apprehended neglect of equall provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion for them) are so sad and pressing, the discontents of the Country (from the oppressions of free quarter) are so full and yet growing, and almost desperate, and the distempers distractions, and dangers threatened by all, these are so vast and emminent, as wee can no longer stand under the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then or blame of them. But if the things here before pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded be not granted and passed effectually (or a certaine course setled according to the effect of them) by the end of this present week; Wee can no longer give account of the Army or other forces in a regualr way; but unlesse wee find satisfaction in our judgements, to take some extraordinary wayes of power; We must let the Soldiery and Kingdome know, that we cannot satisfie their just expectation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon desire that the charge of the Soldiery may be transmitted to others; If the Parliament shall approve, and passe what we have here propounded, we must (for the better prosecution and effecting thereof) add, that the suparlative backwardnesse and obstinacy, or disaffection rather of those within the City, who have thus long with-held their arrears of Taxes, (so long since due to the Army) may not escape either with victory therein, or without examplery suffering (at least) by strict and speedy levying as well the penalties, as the arreares themselves, and (for that purpose) that the Parliament would ressaume the consideration of the Generalls late Letters about that busines, to the Committee of the Army, and reveiw that to the Lord Major and common Councell, wherein the ill consequences both of the wilfull neglect of the thing, and of the Armies withdrawing to a further distance before it be done, or of its continuing longer here abouts, in the delaytory (and perhapps) fruitlesse expectation thereof from the Cities own actings therein may sufficiently appeare.</p>
            <p>To which we adde, that till it be done effectually (and sharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to some) the distribution of the forces to severall Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees to be paid (according to what is before propounded) can neither be effectuall nor safe; And we must therefore desire
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:114603:11"/> that unlesse it be thought sit, that the whole Kingdome should groane still under the oppressions of free quarter, and these adjacent Counties be undone chiefely while those of the City (that occasion al) sit free from any tast of it, there may be no longer stop to the drawing in of the Army, or a considerable part of it to quarter upon them in the City (who had not paid before the said let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, untill they shal have paid both the Arrears and ful penalties; And though our tenderness of that Cities safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; welfare, and our clearness from the least thought of evil towards it, or any base designe to make the least advantage to our selves, or the army by it hath sufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly appeared, as in al our former demeanments, so in our cariage of the business upon our late advance towards it (notwithstanding the just occasions, &amp; great provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons thence so newly given) as also in our innocent march through it, and quiet and patient waiting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout it for those long-due Arreares, without quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering any Souldiers in it; Yet now, in Justice, we cannot but desire that, (besides the levying of the Arreares at last (for which wee have been put to stay so long) there may now likewise some reparation be thought on from the City to the parts adjacent for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove one hundred thousand pounds dammage sustai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned through the Armies attendance here on the Cities defaults and delayes; which reparation, we (if ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessitated thereto, or called upon by the Countrey) must in their behalfe demand from the City to the full; and now also (the rather in order to that) we must ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nestly desire that the proceedings against those Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens and others lately impeacht may be hastned, and out of their fines or confiscations, some part of repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion may be made to the Countries adjacent for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foresaid dammages which the crimes of those persons and others in the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>y d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#oxf" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d first bring upon them; And indeed, without something done against those per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, for example to others, before the Armies with drawing, wee doe not see (when it shall with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw)
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:114603:12"/> with what safety or freedome the Parliament can sit longer at Westminster, especially when wee finde the Common Councell (through the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and Armies lenity) to take the boldnesse al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready (in the face of both) to intercede for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lease and acquitall (or rather justification) of those impeached persons, (who indeed are but fellow-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lionuents (wee doubt) to most of that Councell) as if that so actuall, immediate, and horrid a force upon both and the whole Houses of Parliament, and the levying of Warre in abettment and prosecution thereof, and of that concurrent Treasonable en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement, were already forgotten by them to have beene any crime; the consideration whereof, and of the renewed confidence of Master <hi>Gewen</hi> and some other Members of Parliament, (knowne to have beene partakers, if not principals in the same things) who yet presume, and are suffered to appeare againe in the House (as if in those things there had not been so much fault, as to render them lesse worthy of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing in that highest trust) makes us begin to fear, that, while so much of the same leaven (through le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and moderation) is left behinde, it may shortly spread, til even the worst of the eleven Members (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding their doubled crimes) be again called for in, unlesse the House (by some exclusive resolutions and proceedings) do timely prevent the same; Wee hope therefore the Parl. will weigh these things, and speedily (ere it be too late) consult (at least) their own safety and the Kindoms, if not ours and the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, their poore servants, and something concerned with them (especially) in that affair.</p>
            <p>Next, we again more importunately desire, that those other so neare concernments of the Souldiery (exprest in the Generalls late Remonstrance at the Rendezvouz) may be speedily considered, and fully &amp; effectually provided for; In order to which wee shall here more particularly propound as followeth.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:114603:12"/>
            <p n="1">First, as to the security for Arrears, whereas (in the late Votes or Proposition intended for that purpose) the two thirds of the Lands or Compositions of certain Delinquents assigned towards the said Security, is onely of the Delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents within the three first Qualifications of the 16th Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position; We desire that may be altered so, as to be two Thirds of the Lands or Compositions of all the Delinquents that have not yet compounded. And next we must desire, that Deans and Chapters Lands may be added (with Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viso for reasonable satisfaction or maintenance to such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, as, having a present lawfull Interest in any the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues thereunto belonging, have not forfeited the same by Delinquencie). These Additions are desired, because the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity as yet Voted is justly estimated not to be sufficient, and since all that is propounded is but for Security, if the Security prove to exceed the Arrears really due, the surplu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sage will be free for any other publick use, so as the State will not be damnified by these Additions to the Security. Lastly, (as to this businesse) we desire, that the matters of Security (being resolved on as desired) may be past into Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, and thereby put into a speedie and effectually way of raising Moneys thereupon.</p>
            <p n="2">Secondly, for matter of Indemnity, that if no Indemnity more absolute can be provided (to free the Souldiery from all question for things done in the War) but that they must (in case of question at Law) flie to some Committee or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missioners for relief; It may be provided for the ease of all, that (either under the Grand Committee for Indemnity, or otherwise by the immediate appointment of Parliament) there may be Commissioners in each County impowered to give relief in such Cases, as the Grand Committee now are. And those Commissioners to be such as ordinarily reside in the respective Counties, and mixt of such as have been Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litary Officers to the Parliament, together with such Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants as have appeared active and faithfull for the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the late War; for which purpose we shall (if ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted) offer names; and that there may be a severe Penalty
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:114603:13"/> layed upon Judges, or other Officers of Justice, in case they shall proceed against any contrary to the Ordinance for In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnity.</p>
            <p n="3">Thirdly, that sufficient Provision be made in a certain, and no dishonourable way, for the relief and support of maimed Souldiers, and the Widows and Orphans of men that dyed in the Service, to continue during the lives of the maimed, and widows, and during the minority of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phans; And that the same Commissioners (to be appointed in each County for Indemnity as aforesaid) or others in like manner mixt, may be impowered for this purpose also; And in case of the death of any such Commissioner, or their departure out of their respective Counties, those that sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vive, or remain, may choose new ones to fill up the number.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Thus for the just freedom of Apprentices, who have served the Parliament, there may be a sufficient penalty laid upon Masters refusing or delaying to give the same, when their times are out, accounting the time they have served in the war as part. And that the Apprentise may have his Action at law for that penalty.</p>
            <p n="5">5. For freedom from pressing, that (as no free-man of <hi>England,</hi> may be pressed for any forraigne service, or other then for the immediate defence of it, so) no souldier that hath voluntarily served the Parliament in the late Warre, for the liberties of the Kingdom, may be liable to be prest, for any Military service at all: and that it may be promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed, that a Certificate of his said service as a Voluntier, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the hand and seale of his Collonel, or other Field Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, under whom he hath served, may be a sufficient Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection and discharge to him, from any such pressing.</p>
            <p>Having thus discharged our selves, in those matters which are our most proper, and immediate businesse (the concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Souldiery) and for which we redouble our desires, that the two first (concerning the putting them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to constant pay while continued, and Provision for their Arreares) may be first considered, and immediately settled before any other businesse, and then that the rest of them
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:114603:13"/> may also be provided for, assoon as may be. Now though the two first of these, want not their equall concernments to the Kingdom, (in the present taking of the oppression of free-quarter, preventing the increase of Arrears, and provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or preparing for the more easie and satisfactory dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banding of supernumerages, and thereby the better easing of the Kingdoms burthens by degrees) Yet we cannot in any of our addresses of this kind, so far forget those things we have formerly declared concerning (more purely) the publick interest of the Kingdom and our selves, as members of it, but we must herewith renew our humble and earnest desires, that no time may be lost by the Parliament for the just consideration and dispatch of these things, both for the redresse of Common greivances, releife of the oppressed, and for the liberty, security, quiet and some safe settle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Kingdome; and more especially, that these things of this nature, exprest in the late Remonstrance at the Rendezvous, may in such settlement be fully and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectually provided for, (and that) with as much expediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as may be. And it is our hearts desire and hope, that herein the proceedings and resolutions of the Parliament may be such, and so timeous, as that we may not need any more to remind the Parliament in any of those things which (as far as with truth or any safety to that most ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging interest of the publique, and to those that have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged for it, we may forbeare) we are most unwilling and take no pleasure to meddle in.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Windsor. <date>5. Decem. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>By the appointment of his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency, Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and the Generall Councell of the Army. <hi>John Rushworth</hi> Secretary.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>